Guide to the James H. Karales photographs, 1953-2006 and undated RL.10017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Lower East Side (N.Y), 1969, 1975, 1985, 6 boxes
  - Lower East Side Finished Prints, 17 prints
    - Lower East Side, New York, 1969; (16 x 20 inches) (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P-158)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P149.
    - Lower East Side, New York, 1969; (16 x 20 inches) (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P-159)
      Legacy identifiers: 5264 19:12
    - Lower East Side, New York, 1969; (16 x 20 inches) (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P-160)
      Legacy identifiers: 5264 32:13
    - Lower East Side, New York, 1969; (13 x 19.5 inches) (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P-161)
      Legacy identifiers: 5264 46:24
      Same content as RL-10017-P162 (16 x 20 inches); mounted.
    - Lower East Side, New York, 1969; (16 x 20 inches) (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P-162)
      Legacy identifiers: 46:24; GDC 2786
      Same content as RL-10017-P161 (13 x 19.5 inches).
    - Lower East Side, New York, 1969; (16 x 20 inches) (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P-163)
      Legacy identifiers: 48:5A
    - Lower East Side, New York, 1969; (16 x 20 inches) (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P-164)
      Legacy identifiers: 51:13
    - Lower East Side, New York, 1969; (16 x 20 inches) (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P-165)
      Legacy identifiers: 83:17
- Other Photographic Work, 50 prints
  This series is made up of smaller bodies of work comprising 50 black-and-white prints, 23 of which are single prints, with the others organized into the following original categories established by Karales: Andrea Doria (1956), California (1957); Diana Vreeland (1965); W. Eugene Smith (undated); Prison (undated); and Speech Therapist (undated). Organized in chronological order by project, then within by Gary Davis Collection identifier. The single prints appear last.
  - Andrea Doria, 1956, 1 folder, 5 prints
    Five black-and-white gelatin silver prints, ranging in size from 7.75x13.5 to 11x14 inches Captions in brackets supplied by library staff. The images depict families awaiting survivors from the sinking of the transatlantic passenger ship Andrea Doria off the coast of Massachusetts in 1956.
    No job numbers or roll numbers have been identified.
    - Andrea Doria, 1956; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P166)
      (GDC 2571)
    - Andrea Doria, 1956; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P167)
      (GDC 2572)
    - Andrea Doria, 1956; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P168)
      (GDC 2592)
    - Andrea Doria, 1956; 7.75 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P169)
      (GDC 2620)
    - Andrea Doria, 1956; 8.5 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P170)
      (GDC 2621)
  - California, 1957, 1 folder, 10 images
    Ten gelatin silver prints ranging in size from 8x13.5 to 11x14 inches, comprising nature and landscape shots taken in Carmel and Death Valley, California. Prints from Death Valley capture cloud formations against dark sky. Several prints share similar content; some prints are undated. Where possible, the prints are arranged chronologically by the original roll and frame numbers. If no roll and frame numbers exist, the prints are arranged by the Gary Davis Collection number. Original captions are retained; captions in brackets have been supplied by library staff.
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 8 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P171)
      (18:6/PF29156/GDC 2732)
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 9.5 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P172)
      (GDC 2547)
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 9.5 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P173)
      (GDC 2669)
      Copy of RL-10017-P172
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P174)
      (GDC 2564)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P175 (9 x 13.5 inches)
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P175)
      (GDC 2742/PF29157)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P174 (11 x 14 inches)
      Mounted
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P176)
      (GDC 2727/PF29522)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P177 (11 x 13.5 inches)
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P177)
      (GDC 2731/PF29159)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P176
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P178)
      (GDC 2728/PF29520)
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P179)
      (GDC 2733/PF29532)
    - Cloud Symphony, 1957; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P180)
      (GDC 2734/PF29535)
  - W. Eugene Smith/Juanita Smith, undated, 1 folder, 2 prints
    Two gelatin silver print portraits of Juanita Smith, daughter of photojournalist W. Eugene Smith, about age 5. The prints measure 9x13.5 inches. Captions in brackets have been supplied by library staff.
    - Juanita Smith, 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P184)
      (GDC 2618)
    - Juanita Smith, 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P185)
      (GDC 2658)
  - Prison, undated, 1 folder, 3 prints
    Three gelatin silver prints measuring 9x13.5 inches. Captions in brackets have been supplied by library staff.
    - Prison, 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P186)
      (7:27/GDC 2581)
    - Prison, 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P187)
      (GDC 2580)
    - Prison, 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P188)
      (GDC 2666)
  - Speech Therapist, undated, 1 folder, 4 prints
    Four gelatin silver prints documenting interactions between a speech therapist and his young charges. Images derive from a 1960 Look profile of Richard Adams, an African American speech therapist and social worker who worked with primarily white children in rural Iowa. The prints are undated; they are arranged by the Gary Davis Collection number. Captions in brackets have been supplied by library staff. All prints measure 9x13.5 inches.
    - Speech Therapy, 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P189)
      (GDC 2582/FC 42-22-2A)
    - Speech Therapy, 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P190)
      (GDC 2583/FC 42)
    - Speech Therapy, 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P191)
      (GDC 2593)
    - Speech Therapy, 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P192)
      (GDC 2634/FC 42)
  - Single Prints, 1953-1958 and undated, 5 folders, 23 prints
    Twenty-three gelatin silver prints ranging in size from 7x13.5 to 16x20 inches. Most prints are undated unless otherwise indicated. Several prints share content; some are matted or mounted. The prints are arranged by the Gary Davis Collection number (listed in parentheses immediately under the caption). Original captions have been retained; captions in brackets have been supplied by Rubenstein Library staff.
    Subjects include barns, stilt-walkers, ambulances, and abstract images; places docoumented include Bartlesville, Oklahoma, New Orleans, New York, and Taos, New Mexico.
    - Untitled, 1958; 16 x 20 inches (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P193)
      (GDC 2782/PF23249)
    - Barn, 1953; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P194)
      (GDC 2567)
    - Barn, 1953; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P195)
      (GDC 2671)
      Copy of RL-10017-P194
    - Horse, 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P196)
      (GDC 2677)
    - Still Life, 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P197)
      (GDC 2650)
    - Ambulance, 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P198)
      (GDC 2641)
    - Ambulance, 1953-1958; 7 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P199)
      (GDC 2644)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P198
    - Ambulance, 1953-1958; 7 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P200)
      (GDC 2722/PF29526)
      Same content as print GDC 2641; copy of RL-10017-P199
    - Untitled (law office windows), 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P201)
      (GDC 2570)
      Same content as RL-10017-P202
    - Untitled (law office windows), 1953-1958; 7 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P202)
      (GDC 2705)
      Same content as RL-10017-P201
    - Untitled (car at night), 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P203)
      (GDC 2703)
    - New Orleans, 1953-1958; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P204)
      (GDC 2643)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P205
    - New Orleans, 1953-1958; 16 x 20 inches (Box 28, Image RL-10017-P205)
      (GDC 2779/PF23322)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P204
    - New York, 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P206)
      (GDC 2663)
    - Phillips 66 Building, Bartlesville, OK, 1953-1958; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P207)
      (GDC 2545)
    - Untitled (lights in window), 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P208)
      (GDC 2672)
    - Taos, New Mexico, 1957; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P209)
      (GDC 2662)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P210
    - Taos, New Mexico, 1957; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P210)
      (GDC 2730)
      Same content as print RL-10017-P209
    - Untitled (man on stilts), 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P211)
      (GDC 2616)
    - Untitled (man on stilts), 1953-1958; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P212)
      (GDC 2654)
    - Untitled (man on stilts), 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P213)
      (GDC 2655)
    - Untitled (boy in shopping cart), 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P214)
      (GDC 2675)
    - Tuba Player, 1953-1958; 11 x 14 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P215)
      (GDC 2579)
  - Diana Vreeland, 1965, 1 folder, 3 prints
    Three gelatin silver prints measuring 9x13.5 inches document noted columnist and fashion editor Diana Vreeland at work and in her office at Vogue. The prints are arranged by the Gary Davis Collection number (listed in parentheses immediately under the caption). A Rubenstein Library identification number has been assigned to each print (to the far right of the caption). Original captions are retained; captions in brackets have been supplied by Rubenstein Library staff.
    - Diana Vreeland, 1965; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P181)
      (GDC 2614/VF6658)
    - Diana Vreeland, 1965; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P182)
      (GDC 2665)
    - Diana Vreeland, 1965; 9 x 13.5 inches (Box 26, Image RL-10017-P183)
- Unidentified Photographic Materials, undated, 1 folder
  - Unidentified contact sheets (Box 22)
    Images are of individuals or groups of individuals, and seem to be shot in corporate settings; two sheets appear to be abstract images of beads. These projects are probably commercial work.
- Manuscripts and Printed Materials, 1955-2002 and undated, bulk 1965-2002, 2 boxes and 5 oversize folders
  Contains biographical information in the form of curriculum vitae, interviews, and personal essays on teaching and photography; printed materials such as clippings, flyers, programs, magazine layouts, and other publicity relating to exhibits and published works; and a small group of correspondence, chiefly with publishers. Arranged within subseries and in chronological order.
  - Biographical Information Subseries (oversize), 1999
    - McBride, Caryn, "Through the eyes of the witness," Westchester Generations, 1999 Oct. (Box 30)
  - Biographical Information Subseries, 2000-2002 and undated, 6 folders
    - Interview with James Karales by Sam Stephenson, 2000 Sept. 16 (Box 32)
    - Obituary, The New York Times, 2002 Apr. 5, 2 copies (Box 32)
    - Curriculum vitae, undated (Box 32)
    - Essay on teaching by Karales, undated (Box 32)
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation application, supporting documentation, and curriculum vita, undated (Box 32)
    - Who's Who In America entry submission, undated (Box 32)
  - Civil Rights Subseries, 1965 and undated, 7 folders
    - Negative envelopes for job 2309, 1965 Mar. 26-May 18 (Box 32)
    - "Black emergence," unidentified publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Image for book, "60s book/Selma march," unidentified publication, undated (Box 32)
    - "A march for integration in Selma, Alabama," unidentified publication, undated (Box 32)
    - March from Selma image for exhibit, untitled and undated (Box 32)
    - Photo cropping guide for March from Selma image, untitled and undated (Box 32)
    - Photocopy of March from Selma image, untitled and undated (Box 32)
  - Civil Rights/Martin Luther King, Jr. Subseries, undated, 2 folders
    - Photocopies of contact sheets and photos, undated (Box 32)
    - Photocopies of images, undated (Box 32)
  - Clippings Subseries, 1955-2002, 10 folders
    - Floats, bands and marchers thrill sesqui parade spectators, The Canton Repository, 1955 Aug. 21 (Box 32)
    - Eyes on the prize: the prize is civil rights, Dial, 1987 Jan. (Box 32)
    - Woodstock Times, 1997 Sept. 18 (Box 32)
    - Boxer, Sarah, "Photography review: the night side of black and white," The New York Times, 1999 July 23 (Box 32)
    - Goldberg, Vicki, photography review: Beyond a famous shot, the art of a lifetime, The New York Times, 1999 July 23 (Box 32)
      (3 copies)
    - William Gedney exhibit review, exhibit at Gallery 292, Village Voice, 1999 July 27 (Box 32)
    - Photography exhibit review, exhibit at Howard Greenberg Gallery, Village Voice, 1999 July 28 - Aug. 3 (Box 32)
    - Photography exhibit review, exhibit at Greenberg, The New Yorker, 1999 Aug. 2 (Box 32)
    - William Gedney exhibit review, exhibit at Gallery 292, The New Yorker, 1999 Aug. 2 (Box 32)
    - Westchester Magazine, 2002 (Box 32)
    - Rye Magazine, 2009 (Box 32)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, undated (Box 32)
  - Clippings Subseries (oversize), 1987-1997, 4 folders
    - Reynolds, Barbara, TV series teaches how a movement is made, USA Today, 1987 Jan. 21 (Box 29)
    - Goldberg, Vicki, photography review: Remembering the faces in the Civil Rights struggle, "The New York Times, 1994 July 17 (Box 29)
    - Zimmerman, Kevin, PBS 25th anniversary: Making room for quality time: upscale, loyal viewership remains intact; solid fare plays key role in success, unknown publication, 1994 Mar. 14-20 (Box 31)
    - Norklun, Kathi, Looks like America: classic images from Look magazine at Coffey Gallery, Woodstock Times, 1997 Sept. 18 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1971-1999 and undated, 8 folders
    Folders of letters and notes mostly concerning permissions for publication of images. In some cases, Karales was not the direct recipient of the letters, but was copied on the exchange.
    - Smith, Claire, Harold Ober Associates, 1971 July 20 (Box 32)
    - Maxey, David, 1971 July 23 and undated (Box 32)
    - Zerby, Donna P., Corporate Communications, Scott, 1971 Nov. 18 (Box 32)
    - Matthews, Margaret, Reader's Digest, 1982 Mar. 15 (Box 32)
    - Durland, Steven, General Manager, Astro Artz, Inc., 1983 Aug. 22 (Box 32)
    - Boston Publishing Company, 1984 Mar.-1985 Aug. (Box 32)
    - Courtwright, David, Professor of History, University of North Florida, 1999 Jan. 25 (Box 32)
    - Carlos from Michigan, undated (Box 32)
  - Logging Subseries, 1961 and undated, 2 folders
    - Smith, Jerome B., Supervisor, Visual Information, Weyerhaeuser Company, Correspondence, 1961 Oct. 4 (Box 32)
    - Weyerhaeuser Company, exhibit, undated (Box 32)
      Includes photo captions printed on company letter-head.
  - Lower East Side Subseries, 1969 and undated, 4 folders
    - Negative envelopes for job 5264, 1969 Aug. 4-Dec. 8 (Box 32)
    - Excerpts from interview with Father Bruce Ritter, undated (Box 32)
    - "An explosion of aggression," unidentified publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Photocopies of images, undated (Box 32)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Subseries, 1983 and undated, 3 folders
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. from Montgomery to Memphis, exhibit pamphlet, New York State Museum, 1983 Jan. 15 (Box 32)
    - King: a photobiography of Martin Luther King, Jr., exhibit pamphlet, Viking Studio, undated (Box 32)
    - Unidentified publication, undated (Box 32)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Subseries (oversize), 1999
    - Pamphlet, National Historic Site, National Park Service, U.S. Department of the Interior, 1999 (Box 30)
  - Other Printed Materials Subseries, 1972-1999 and undated, 11 folders
    - Photocopies of slides of New York City, Pine, New York, Croton, New York, and Townshend, Vermont, 1972-1980 (Box 32)
    - James H. Karales: an adventure in photojournalism, exhibit at Rizzoli Gallery, N.Y., New York, 1980 May 29-June 30 (Box 32)
    - Images from SEI Corporation annual report (images taken by Karales), 1987 (Box 32)
    - Miscellaneous images, 1993 Oct. 20 and undated (Box 32)
    - "Look again: photojournalism by Look magazine staffers: Charlotte Brooks, Phillip Harrington, James H. Karales, Tony Vaccaro," exhibit at the Coffey Gallery, Kingston, New York, 1997 Sept. 6-Oct. 1 (Box 32)
    - Witness (exhibit), 1999 June 25-July 31 (Box 32)
    - Map of New York and New Jersey, undated (Box 32)
    - 1965 (Columbia record cover), undated (Box 32)
    - Picture credits and acknowledgments, unknown publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Sixties (photocopy of poster/pamphlet), undated (Box 32)
    - Special pre-schooling for 5-year-olds with learning disabilities, undated (Box 32)
  - Other Printed Materials Subseries (oversize), 1983
    - Exhibit poster, New York State Museum, 1983 (Box 28)
  - Published Works Subseries (oversize), 1955-1965 and undated, 5 folders
    - Karales, James H., Ohio sub hunters, Cleveland Plain Dealer Pictorial Magazine, 1955 Aug. 21, 2 copies (Box 31)
    - Castan, Sam and James H. Karales, Vietnam, Look, 1965 Apr. 6 (Box 31)
    - Castan, Sam and James H. Karales, Saigon: stained pearl of the orient, Look, 1966 May 17 (Box 31)
      (2 copies)
    - Spike, Robert W., Our churches' sin against the Negro, Look, 1965 May 18 (Box 31)
    - Castan, Sam and James H. Karales, The new New York: victims of welfare, unknown publication, undated (Box 31)
  - Published Works Subseries, 1964-2000 and undated, 18 folders
    - Brooks, Charlotte, Look Editorial Preview, 1964 Jan. 28 and Inside Look, 1967 Feb. 3 (Box 32)
    - [Outer space ghost story], Look, 1966 Feb. 22 (Box 32)
    - 1966 All-American cities, Look Editorial Preview, 1967 Apr. 18 (Box 32)
    - Chapter 2: What teaching is like, unknown publication, 1979 June 14 (Box 32)
    - Negroes-history/March to Selma, American Heritage, 1982 June/July (Box 32)
    - The children's crusade saves the day and Bloody Sunday in Selma, unknown publications, 1997 Apr. 24 (Box 32)
    - Photocopies of images from the civil rights series, unknown publication, 2000 Feb. 17 (Box 32)
    - Chapter 6: African Americans, the struggle for civil rights, unknown publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Chapter 32: Leadership of the 1960s, unknown publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Dulli, five poems, unknown publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Helping with drug misuse, unknown publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Images from book on career options, unknown publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Images from copy about payroll, undated (Box 32)
    - The march from Selma to Montgomery finally begins, Martin Luther King, Jr., undated (Box 32)
    - Marchers, Selma to Montgomery, Alabama, 1965, unknown publicationundated (Box 32)
    - [Moral therapy in Gheel, Belgium], unknown publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Pembroke, Herbert, 10.4 civil rights demonstration, unknown publication, undated (Box 32)
    - Williams, Juan, Eyes on the prize: America's civil rights years, 1954-1965, New York: Viking Penguin Inc., undated (Box 32)
  - Published Works Subseries (oversize), 1965
    - Look magazine, 1965 Apr. 6, "Vietnam" (Box 30)
  - Rendville, Ohio Subseries, undated, 3 folders
    - Exhibit materials, undated, 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Research notes on Rendville, Ohio and Perry County, Ohio, undated (Box 33)
  - Vietnam Subseries, 1963-1968 and undated, 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Negative envelopes from jobs 1610 and 2735, 1963 Nov. 18-1968 Dec. 10 (Box 33)
    - Photocopies of contact sheets and prints, undated (Box 33)
- Audiovisual Materials, 2000-2006 and undated, 3 folders
  A variety of recordings and still images: a video (VHS) of photographs by Karales; a CD-R of an interview conducted with Karales on September 16, 2000; an audiocassette of remarks made by Sam Stephenson at an opening of a Karales exhibit at Duke, April 2005; and a CD-R from 2006 with JPEG files of 31 photos from the Vietnam series.
  - Audiovisual materials, 2000-2006 and undated (Box 33)